<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-erdtman-jose-cleartext-jws-00" ipr="trust200902">
 <front>
   <title abbrev="draft-erdtman-jose-cleartext-jws">
     Cleartext JSON Web Signature (JWS)
   </title>

   <author fullname="Samuel Erdtman" initials="S." surname="Erdtman">
     <organization>Spotify AB</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Birger Jarlsgatan 61, 4tr</street>
         <code>113 56</code> <city>Stockholm</city>
         <country>Sweden</country>
       </postal>
       <email>erdtman@spotify.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Anders Rundgren" initials="A." surname="Rundgren">
     <organization>Independent</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street></street>
         <code></code> <city>Montpellier</city>
         <country>France</country>
       </postal>
       <email>anders.rundgren.net@gmail.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
	<uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

   <date year="2018" />

   <area>Security</area>

   <workgroup>JSON Object Signing and Encryption (JOSE)</workgroup>

   <keyword>
     JOSE, Signing, Encryption, Cleartext
   </keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>
       Cleartext JSON Web Signature (JWS) represents signed data as cleartext JSON objects.
       The signature is included in the JSON object to be signed.
       Cleartext JWS builds on JWS <xref target="RFC7515"/>, JWA
       <xref target="RFC7518"/> and JWK <xref target="RFC7517"/>,
       including for representations of header parameters, algorithms, and cryptographic keys.
       Serialization of the JSON object to be signed uses the predictable
       serialization defined in ECMAScript version 6.
       Cleartext JWS reuses data structures and semantics from JWS whenever practical and reasonable.
       Cryptographic algorithms and identifiers used by this specification
       are defined in the JSON Web Algorithms specification.
     </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

<middle>
  <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
    <t>
      Cleartext JSON Web Signature (JWS) represents signed data as cleartext JSON <xref target="RFC8259"/> objects.
      The signature is included in the JSON object to be signed.
      By enveloping the signature in the JSON object to be signed, it is easy to
      inspect data in transit and when archived, integrity can be guaranteed.
      Cryptographic algorithms and identifiers used by this specification
      are defined in the JSON Web Algorithms (JWA) <xref target="RFC7518" /> specification.
    </t>
    <t>
      Cleartext JWS reuses constructs from JWS, JWA, and JWK whenever practical and reasonable.
      Header parameters from JWS, algorithms from JWA, and the key representation JWK are used.
      There are two essential differences from JWS.
      First, Cleartext JWS signatures are included in the signed data.
      Second, Cleartext JWS depends on predictable JSON Serialization
      rather than base64url encoding the data to be signed.
      The table below shows the primary characteristics of the JWS variants:
      </t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">JWS</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Cleartext JWS</ttcol>
        <c>Data&nbsp;to&nbsp;be&nbsp;Signed</c>
        <c>Any&nbsp;type and&nbsp;format</c>
        <c>
          Non-intrusive signature object
          for inclusion in arbitrary JSON
          and JavaScript objects
        </c>
        <c>Encoding&nbsp;of&nbsp;Signed&nbsp;Data</c>
        <c>Base64Url</c>
        <c>None</c>
        <c>Encoding&nbsp;of&nbsp;Header&nbsp;Data</c>
        <c>Base64Url</c>
        <c>None</c>
        <c>URL Friendly</c>
        <c>Core&nbsp;feature</c>
        <c>Out of scope</c>
      </texttable>
    <t>
      In the following example, there are a few things to note.
      The signature is included in the data (aka enveloped signature).
      The members in the <spanx style="verb">__cleartext_signature</spanx> object are the JWS
      header parameters.
      The <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx> member contains the base64url encoded signature bytes.
      </t>
    <t>
      <figure align="center">
        <artwork>
<![CDATA[{
  "iss": "joe",
  "exp": 1300819380,
  "escapeMe": "\u20ac$\u000F\u000aA'\u0042\u0022\u005c\\\"\/",
  "numbers": [1e+30,4.5,6],
  "__cleartext_signature": {
    "alg": "ES256",
    "kid": "example.com:p256",
    "signature": "pXP0GFHms0SntctNk1G1pHZfccVYdZkmAJktY_hpMsI
                  AckzX7wZJIJNlsBzmJ1_7LmKATiW-YHHZjsYdT96JZw"
  }
}]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </t>
      <t>Note that the <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx> value was cut in two to cope with RFC line length constraints.</t>
    <t>
      The key specified in <xref target="example.com:p256"/> can be used for verifying the example signature.
    </t><t>
    Note: Recreating the example signature using the example private key would normally
    result in a different <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx> value
    since ECDSA relies on random data for signature generation.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Terminology">
    <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
      when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="SignatureObject" title="The Signature Object">
    <t>
      When signing JSON data with Cleartext JWS a JSON object with the
      JWS Header Parameters are created and placed within the JSON data to be
      signed. In addition to the already defined JWS Header Parameters
      Cleartext JWS defines two new Header Parameters <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx>
      for the base64url encoded signature value and <spanx style="verb">signers</spanx>
      to support multiple signers within the same signature object.
    </t>
    <t>
      The identifier for the Cleartext Signature Object in the JSON data to be
      signed MUST be <spanx style="verb">__cleartext_signature</spanx>, unless
      the application specifies that a different identifier is to be used.
    </t>
  <section anchor="SignatureScope" title="Signature Scope">
    <t>
      The scope of a signature, what is actually signed, comprises all
      properties including possible child objects of the JSON object holding
      the signature property except for the <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx> member.
    </t>
  </section>
    <section anchor="SignatureHeaderParameter" title="The &quot;signature&quot; Header Parameter">
      <t>
        The <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx> Header Parameter contains the
        base64url-encoded JWS Signature as a string.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="SignersHeaderParameter" title="The &quot;signers&quot; Header Parameter">
      <t>
        The optional <spanx style="verb">signers</spanx> Header Parameter contains an
        array of signatures.  See <xref target="MultipleSignatures" />.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="ProducingConsumingCleartextJWSs" title="Producing and Consuming Cleartext JWSs">
    <section anchor="MessageSignatureMACComputation" title="Message Signature or MAC Computation">
      <t>
        To create a Cleartext JWS, the following steps are performed.  The order of the
        steps is not significant in cases where there are no dependencies
        between the inputs and outputs of the steps.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Create the JSON object to be signed.
          </t>
          <t>
            Create the <spanx style="verb">__cleartext_signature</spanx> object with the header parameters to be used and add it
            as a top-level member to the object to be signed with the key
            <spanx style="verb">__cleartext_signature</spanx>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Serialize the object to be signed using the Serialization and
            normalization rules defined in
            <xref target="Serialization" />.
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the JWS Signature in the manner defined for the particular
            algorithm being used over the serialized object to be signed. The
            <spanx style="verb">alg</spanx> (algorithm) Header Parameter MUST be present in the <spanx style="verb">__cleartext_signature</spanx>
            member, with the algorithm value accurately representing the
            algorithm used to construct the JWS Signature.
          </t>
          <t>
            Add the <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx> member to the signature object with the encoded
            Cleartext JWS signature and assign it the string value BASE64URL(JWS Signature).
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="MessageSignatureMACValidation" title="Message Signature or MAC Validation">
      <t>
        When validating a Cleartext JWS, the following steps are performed.  The order
        of the steps is not significant in cases where there are no
        dependencies between the inputs and outputs of the steps.  If any of
        the listed steps fails, then the input MUST be rejected.
      </t>
      <t>
        When there are multiple Cleartext JWS Signature values, it is an application
        decision which of the Cleartext JWS Signature values must successfully validate
        for the Cleartext JWS to be accepted.  In some cases, all must successfully
        validate, or the Cleartext JWS will be considered invalid.  In other cases,
        only a specific Cleartext JWS Signature value needs to be successfully
        validated.  However, in all cases, at least one Cleartext JWS Signature value
        MUST successfully validate, or the Cleartext JWS MUST be considered invalid.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Parse JSON data including enveloped signature.
          </t>
          <t>
            Verify that the implementation understands and can process all
            fields that it is required to support, whether required by this
            specification, by the algorithm being used, or by the <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx>
            Header Parameter value, and that the values of those parameters
            are also understood and supported.
          </t>
          <t>
            Save and remove the <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx> member from the signature object and
            base64url-decode the encoded representation of the Cleartext JWS Signature.
          </t>
          <t>
            Serialize and normalize the signed object including the signature
            object, by following the rules in
            <xref target="Serialization" />.
          </t>
          <t>
            Validate the Cleartext JWS Signature against the Cleartext JWS Signing Input, i.e., the
            Serialized and Normalized data, in the manner defined for the
            algorithm being used, which MUST be accurately represented by the
            value of the <spanx style="verb">alg</spanx> (algorithm) Header Parameter value,
	    which MUST be present. Record whether the
            validation succeeded or not.
          </t>
          <t>
            Return a result indicating whether or not the Cleartext JWS was
            successfully validated.
          </t>
          <t>
            For later validation of the signed object, put back the <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx>
            member back into the JSON data structure.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Serialization" title="Serialization and Normalization">
      <t>
        When having header parameters in cleartext serialization of them needs to be
        consistent across platforms. JSON <xref target="RFC8259" /> by itself does not produce
        predictable serialization of data. However, ES6 <xref target="ES6"/> defines how to produce
        JSON that is predictable. By following the ES6 serialization directives,
        one gets predictable results, i.e., the JSON serializer MUST follow the
        directives set out by ES6 when serializing data. The rules defined below
        take the essence from the ES6 specification and list what that means
        in practical terms.
      </t>
      <t>
        Rules for serialization:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            The original property serialization order MUST be preserved as
            described by ECMAScript section 9.1.12.
          </t>
          <t>
            JSON data of the type <spanx style="verb">Number</spanx>, MUST be processed according to
            ECMAScript section 7.1.12.1.
          </t>
          <t>
            Property names MUST be unique.
          </t>
          <t>
            Whitespace must be removed which in practical terms means removal
            of all characters outside of quoted strings having a value of x09,
            x0a, x0d or x20.
          </t>
          <t>
            JSON '\/' escape sequences within quoted strings must be treated as
            "degenerate" equivalents to '/' by rewriting them.
          </t>
          <t>
            Unicode escape sequences (\uhhhh) within quoted strings must be
            adjusted as follows: If the Unicode value falls within the
            traditional ASCII control character range (0x00-0x1f and 0x7f), it must
            be rewritten in lowercase hexadecimal notation unless it is one
            of the predefined JSON escapes (\" \\ \b \f \n \r \t) because
            the latter have precedence. If the Unicode value is outside of
            the ASCII control character range, it must be replaced by the
            corresponding Unicode character. See ECMAScript section 24.3.2.2.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        If these rules are applied to the example signature, it should result in
        the following string
        (with line wraps between elements for display purposes only):
        </t>
      <t>
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[{"iss":"joe","exp":1300819380,
"escapeMe":"\u20ac$\u000f\nA'B\"\\\\\"/",
"numbers":[1e+30,4.5,6],"__cleartext_signature":
{"alg":"ES256","kid":"example.com:p256"}}]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>Note: \u20ac denotes the Euro symbol which is a single character, currently not
      displayable &quot;as is&quot; in RFCs.</t>
      <t>
        The final step is converting the textual output into an UTF-8 formatted array.
        Applied to the sample this should yield the following bytes here shown in decimal notation:
        </t>
      <t>
           123, 34, 105, 115, 115, 34, 58, 34, 106,
          111, 101, 34, 44, 34, 101, 120, 112, 34,
          58, 49, 51, 48, 48, 56, 49, 57, 51,
          56, 48, 44, 34, 101, 115, 99, 97, 112,
          101, 77, 101, 34, 58, 34, 226, 130, 172,
          36, 92, 117, 48, 48, 48, 102, 92, 110,
          65, 39, 66, 92, 34, 92, 92, 92, 92,
          92, 34, 47, 34, 44, 34, 110, 117, 109,
          98, 101, 114, 115, 34, 58, 91, 49, 101,
          43, 51, 48, 44, 52, 46, 53, 44, 54,
          93, 44, 34, 95, 95, 99, 108, 101, 97,
          114, 116, 101, 120, 116, 95, 115, 105, 103,
          110, 97, 116, 117, 114, 101, 34, 58, 123,
          34, 97, 108, 103, 34, 58, 34, 69, 83,
          50, 53, 54, 34, 44, 34, 107, 105, 100,
          34, 58, 34, 101, 120, 97, 109, 112, 108,
          101, 46, 99, 111, 109, 58, 112, 50, 53,
          54, 34, 125, 125
      </t>
      <section anchor="ES6Interoperability" title="ES6+ Interoperability">
        <t>
          For JavaScript optimization reasons, ES6+'s JSON.parse() internally
          rearranges the order of properties with names expressed as integers, making a
          parsed JSON string like '{"2":"First", "A":"Second","1":"Third"}' actually serialize as
          '{"1":"Third","2":"First","A":"Second"}'. Due to this fact, signature creators MUST
          "emulate" this scheme since this behavior is not
          intended to be an additional requirement to support by JSON tools in
          general in order to use this specification.   The easiest way
          accomplishing this is to programmatically make sure that possible
          numeric property names always are created first and added in ascending
          order.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="MultipleSignatures" title="Multiple Signatures">
      <t>
        Multiple signatures enable different keys to independently of each other
        add a signature to a JSON object.
      </t>
      <t>
        The normalization procedure is essentially the same as for single
        signatures but must also take the following in account as well:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            There MUST be an additional Cleartext JWS Header parameter <spanx style="verb">signers</spanx>, holding an array
            of signature constructs.
          </t>
          <t>
            Each signature requires its own normalization process. During this
            process, the other signature constructs MUST (temporarily) be removed.
          </t>
          <t>
            The normalized data MUST include the array brackets ([]) but MUST NOT
            include the comma separating the signature constructs.
          </t>
          <t>
            A signature construct is equivalent to an ordinary Cleartext JWS object,
            but MAY exclude the <spanx style="verb">alg</spanx> Header parameter which then
            MUST be declared in the Cleartext JWS object itself.  Using the latter arrangement,
            all enclosed signature constructs MUST use the same algorithm as well as not
            specifying the <spanx style="verb">alg</spanx> Header parameter.
            See <xref target="multipleglobalalg"/> for an example.
          </t>
          <t>
            If a <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx> Header parameter is specified in
            the Cleartext JWS object itself, this declaration MUST be applied to
            all signature constructs. Such a declaration MUST NOT be combined
            with <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx> Header parameters in
            the enclosed signature constructs.
            See <xref target="multipleglobalcrit"/> for an example.
          </t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The following example shows a multiply signed object:
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[{
  "iss": "joe",
  "exp": 1300819380,
  "escapeMe": "\u20ac$\u000F\u000aA'\u0042\u0022\u005c\\\"\/",
  "numbers": [1e+30,4.5,6],
  "__cleartext_signature": {
    "signers": [{
      "alg": "ES256",
      "kid": "example.com:p256",
      "signature": "83gr5rmjKgngLTaPpxuQWiZaQmlQ555jLHNcZLmcBpg
                    X7JZLeqrNhIrQRg3jTsNwh1RuibDYBzCsaxVUkhGEKg"
    },{
      "alg": "RS256",
      "kid": "example.com:r2048",
      "signature": "PVQeL8XtjnetambQe98FuMBDuijwWTIFXouyNjL8WX0
                    WvamWkHjv34Iz8VOHHWr9w8t14FXJJuQ22j-h5BR7qP
                    xE7cBVS8XSltR7VvcNidfn-r-TtAVwDwn7Iz_Gk-RI7
                    QIv4ctbreYt1myG64Ikw38OEmNURCxzf9h9w3tvA3R8
                    ZE3MYgELFaQRowSW92JC1HhGZRijzHoIzvH6l_GULP_
                    hf7kggwFNtRrzN8DLXbhBhGaoP-O0cNZsCWY2hbNU6L
                    7km6bdrqHdq88DSOEGg_-5T6qUsIAYbmCgUK7XBi2q-
                    DRPQZYnxr5570mj9Nkh0hpZ-VfAC2ftbzxFAB7ZYg"
    }]
  }
}]]></artwork>
        </figure>
    </t>
      <t>
        The ECDSA signature can be validated using the key specified in <xref target="example.com:p256"/>,
      while the RSA signature can be validated using the key specified in <xref target="example.com:r2048"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section anchor="IANAJSONHeaderParametersRegistry" title="JSON Header Parameters Registry">
        <t>
          This section registers the <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx>
          and <spanx style="verb">signers</spanx> header parameter in the "JSON Web
          Signature and Encryption Header Parameters" registry
          in the manner described in <xref target="RFC7515"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="IANAJSONHeaderParametersRegistryContents" title="Registry Contents">
          <t>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>Header Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">signature</spanx></t>
              <t>Header Parameter Description: The base64url-encoded signature value.</t>
              <t>Header Parameter Usage Location(s): <spanx style="verb">CT-JWS</spanx></t>
              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
              <t>Specification Document(s): <xref target="SignatureHeaderParameter"/></t>
            </list>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>Header Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">signers</spanx></t>
              <t>Header Parameter Description: List of signers, each with a set of headers and a signature.</t>
              <t>Header Parameter Usage Location(s): <spanx style="verb">CT-JWS</spanx></t>
              <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
              <t>Specification Document(s): <xref target="SignersHeaderParameter"/></t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
      This specification does (to the authors' knowledge), not introduce
      additional vulnerabilities over what is specified for JWS
      <xref target="RFC7515"/>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>
      This document builds on the work done in the JOSE WG so a big thanks goes out
      to all involved in that work. It is specifically inspired by JWS, so a
      special thanks to the authors of that document, Michael B. Jones, John Bradley,
      and Nat Sakimura.
      </t><t>
      Building on ES6 number normalization was originally
      proposed by James Manger. This ultimately led to
      the adoption of the entire ES6 JSON processing model.
    </t>
  </section>
 </middle>

 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8259'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7515'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7517'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7518'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

     <reference anchor="ES6" target="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/6.0/ECMA-262.pdf">
       <front>
         <title>ECMAScript 2015 Language Specification</title>
         <author>
           <organization>Ecma International</organization>
         </author>
         <date/>
       </front>
     </reference>
   </references>

   <section anchor="TestVectors" title="Test Vectors">
     <t>This section contains a set of test vectors sharing a common characteristic,
     long lines are sliced in order to cope with RFC line length constraints.</t>
   <section anchor="multipleglobalalg" title="Multiple Signature with Global &quot;alg&quot; Header">
     <t>
     <figure align="center">
        <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "iss": "joe",
  "exp": 1300819380,
  "escapeMe": "\u20ac$\u000F\u000aA'\u0042\u0022\u005c\\\"\/",
  "numbers": [1e+30,4.5,6],
  "__cleartext_signature": {
    "alg": "ES512",
    "signers": [{
      "kid": "example.com:p256",
      "signature": "zjf2MzEesdIudTk0k9osa0um5ffzU-oM_8Z-mKHFmZxCRvpl4
                    1lX2KUt5a742px_cTsG7sw-Kh8_xJuUMX97Kg"
    },{
      "kid": "example.com:p384",
      "signature": "jTWnzmAcC34zOpTvvg7vuqLECUOqS6UMQcjwM24w7DwHz7nXQ
                    e17eFYTjJWE-w_Nnw3sosYM6c6J9ABFOGoKx70cRPNQQ8WHfT
                    zAyfTBxMBWtUR5PKWi5hJWUDeMnRS0"
    }]
  }
}]]></artwork>
    </figure>
     </t><t>
       The first signature can be verified using the key specified in <xref target="example.com:p256"/>,
     while the second signature can be verified using the key specified in <xref target="example.com:p384"/>.
     </t>
   </section>
   <section anchor="multipleglobalcrit" title="Multiple Signature with Global &quot;crit&quot; Header">
     <t>
     <figure align="center">
        <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "iss": "joe",
  "exp": 1300819380,
  "escapeMe": "\u20ac$\u000F\u000aA'\u0042\u0022\u005c\\\"\/",
  "numbers": [1e+30,4.5,6],
  "__cleartext_signature": {
    "crit": ["otherExt","https://example.com/extension"],
    "signers": [{
      "alg": "ES256",
      "kid": "example.com:p256",
      "otherExt": "Other Data",
      "signature": "S9PqQU5z5zThIGUvErzf7oo8EetiUFEI1v8flisWJzw0HqqY-
                    OuT_pDq1rG4gsSRAFjrazurl4NGyyxcPfeXzw"
    },{
      "alg": "RS256",
      "kid": "example.com:r2048",
      "otherExt": "Cool Stuff",
      "https://example.com/extension": {
        "life-is-great": true
      },
      "signature": "O-cnYTtgvyGmgX1YMQkcnRE0lnBw1EduMNVpdblKP-Iy0S143
                    BBvXrCQoEW9oTkQm7X9wkJoohWQyU4qvojoxQxmf6GQ0tEXEI
                    HqN7ixkPh_3ySXTl-gKTPiA5UL-GV44AS-k6N71qp8XhLORmU
                    m68UlTWBZaOXL0JTGjsCyGpuwNiAQbx39ZbjabvGq4NfpPIQC
                    2yjx_SKoPMiia54Mp0hz8U_S3oyAmHrG2mKFYrJ7k43aeDHK1
                    RNRu8XrW2w-Ffh4KigpClAq4q272ZSsjizfYPPjW3gqInjMZz
                    Qd8yZj5Bi5vCDcBOEKZMDoog-UzIy8SbZNl85TlkhK70oNRQ"
    }]
  }
}]]></artwork>
    </figure>
     </t>
     <t>
       The first signature can be verified using the key specified in <xref target="example.com:p256"/>,
     while the second signature can be verified using the key specified in <xref target="example.com:r2048"/>.
   </t>
   </section>
   <section anchor="example.com:p256" title="EC Key &quot;example.com:p256&quot;">
     <t>EC private key, here expressed in JWK notation:</t>
     <t>
     <figure align="center">
        <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "kid": "example.com:p256",
  "kty": "EC",
  "crv": "P-256",
  "x": "censDzcMEkgiePz6DXB7cDuwFemshAFR90UNVQFCg8Q",
  "y": "xq8rze6ewG0-eVcSF72J77gKiD0IHnzpwHaU7t6nVeY",
  "d": "nEsftLbi5u9pI8B0-drEjIuJzQgZie3yeqUR3BwWDl4"
}]]></artwork>
    </figure>
     </t>
   </section>
   <section anchor="example.com:p384" title="EC Key &quot;example.com:p384&quot;">
     <t>EC private key, here expressed in JWK notation:</t>
     <t>
     <figure align="center">
        <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "kid": "example.com:p384",
  "kty": "EC",
  "crv": "P-384",
  "x": "GLfdsvEwphRzS_twup7UFPVOk7_CKgHZ7dt_fJ2QHPBdJa1c5pfJcRIWTfT0l
        pg9",
  "y": "ovA5_QXmFbj9U4pjZ1AX_ZdVyIRZUBWW9cuZda_tupKfWQfmcQHzDmHGHbxl9
        Xxl",
  "d": "Qsgq80kMs40sAn1gB7gLxAk1se37Kmh9AG18wWZ3SqgcPPRq1wwidNTi866Gt
        4_0"
}]]></artwork>
    </figure>
     </t>
   </section>
     <section anchor="example.com:r2048" title="RSA Key &quot;example.com:r2048&quot;">
     <t>RSA private key, here expressed in JWK notation:</t>
     <t>
     <figure align="center">
        <artwork><![CDATA[{
  "kid": "example.com:r2048",
  "kty": "RSA",
  "n": "hFWEXArvaZEpSP5qNX7x4C4Hl28GJQTNvnDwkfqiWs63kXbdyPeS06bz6GnY3
        tfQ_093nGauWsimqKBmGAGMPtsV83Qxw1OIeO4ujbIIb9pema0qtVqs0MWlHx
        klZGFkYfAmbuEUFxYDeLDHe0bkkXbSlB7_t8pCSvc8HLgHjEQjYOlFRwjR0D-
        uLo-xgsCbpmCtYkB5lcT_zFgpRgY4zJNLSv7GZiz2S4Fc5ArGjd34lL47-L8b
        ozuYjqNOv9sqX0Zgll5XaJ1ndvr7UqZu1xQFgm38reoM3IarBP_SkEFbt_v9i
        ak602VO3k28fQhMaocP7JWR2YLT3kZM0-WTFw",
  "e": "AQAB",
  "d": "Q6iBYpnIrB2mkQZagP1lZuvBv9_osVaSZpLRvKD7DxhvbDTs0coaTJIoVCSB1
        _VZip8zlUg-TnYWF1Liv9VSwfQ7ddxrcOUtej60mId0ntNz2HhbxJsWjiru8E
        ZoArl0nEovLDNxlRgRMEyZwOKPC_xHT6nFrk7_s9pR5pEEcubGLAVBKnLCoPd
        Lr-CBjCvWfJo73W5AZxoSb8MdWQOi5viXHURpr1Y_uBRsMuclovM56Vt05etM
        sB1AbcTLUDwAuYrZWa1c08ql60ft7b3v6Q_rCL7EHtFU3PHAuP0mV7tM5BfAP
        f4T0g9pbr4GOw7eqQCiYgPFE7gmCR_PDxv5YQ",
  "p": "6DIM343hAtj1hQprJaVQ3T8YeIytIQ7Ma544C0A8BX-irjJfARy4fAlTSyBFe
        auZ0WdbMGtKpAIgNVmfCfuP7W1bXw7UaxpqsQlbw54K1VtBs8xG-lee_2YQ3l
        UlIiC1at6L0jxWYNkvp-LIfU2F5ZQir5ZWVXwgdMcgoNBABMc",
  "q": "keacq0goV7pAtG2h33OAk-XOSclIF1agvEMMOKuud5V-vGQ6OaYldlYqZmSGg
        F7RVlX0GZO70nPqatjd2G-tI8wEq5K_xmLQurUPFW8g___z0CTgJ62KbjFxCt
        Gny5rsObX9im6cCc_EOtWZRaApzO8ykxfo1QcEjT4k1na7DzE",
  "dp": "nPmJPnFal2Q5x_GdMlwq6QhI8OaZ_OlWRcM3PFP2v_jj8ERZehUCm8hqKTXu
         Ai2C1dC8E2XVlj9hqu-l10fcq7Tsurz52laHnpwnD35-8HK7XmRR79jgwuUr
         rkN90S6vt0ow2La15s-tqiBlTmDkjqqxMGfAghZiktA0PMPNI-0",
  "dq": "D3c1lkZw2FPK9hVE-m3A7GyIwHOQq8CoCyzER-GS_eQf6hJpxaCiCfg6SF5R
         j5v9brxvwqJRX46gA7F3WrED1m6S9Cj7ISlqXNBCiBAenGRiUOcHx8zyhpnB
         FNeChOeoMLnk5V6yNawLbf0kYSgIJkwYvVTkfmhfCCXVO9KcI5E",
  "qi": "wV0NzfCakfog1NFjtPzcga1MtkpizgPkxcP9LjNdvXW2YQZhM6GIEGjsu3iv
         TrHrrM-4_bTQHOoTtfIY7wdqBKlwQTJOI0dH9FbNJ4ecGojRwgv83TN8aNKh
         17Tt44jI5oibs2P-31B_VW9R1wwhnnOuCYpABfoSbtHIoCRme5I"
}]]></artwork>
    </figure>
     </t>
   </section>
 </section>
 </back>
</rfc>
