<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-erdtman-jose-cleartext-jwe-00" ipr="trust200902">
 <front>
   <title abbrev="draft-erdtman-jose-cleartext-jwe">
     Cleartext JSON Web Encryption (JWE)
   </title>

   <author fullname="Samuel Erdtman" initials="S." surname="Erdtman">
     <organization>Spotify AB</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Birger Jarlsgatan 61, 4tr</street>
         <code>113 56</code> <city>Stockholm</city>
         <country>Sweden</country>
       </postal>
       <email>erdtman@spotify.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Anders Rundgren" initials="A." surname="Rundgren">
     <organization>Independent</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street></street>
         <code></code> <city></city>
         <country>France</country>
       </postal>
       <email>anders.rundgren.net@gmail.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
	<uri>http://self-issued.info/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

   <date year="2018" />

   <area>Security</area>

   <workgroup>JSON Object Signing and Encryption (JOSE)</workgroup>

   <keyword>
     JOSE, Signing, Encryption, Cleartext
   </keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>
       Cleartext JSON Web Encryption (JWE) represents encrypted content using JSON data structures.
       With the use of the predictable serialization defined in ECMAScript version 6,
       protected header parameters can remain in cleartext.
       Cleartext JWE reuses data structures and semantics from JWE whenever practical and reasonable.
       Cryptographic algorithms and identifiers used by this specification
       are defined in the JSON Web Algorithms specification.
     </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

<middle>
  <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
    <t>
      Cleartext JSON Web Encryption (JWE) represents encrypted content using JSON-based data structures.
      With the use of predictable serialization
      defined in ECMAScript version 6 <xref target="ES6"/> protected header parameters
      can remain cleartext. Cleartext JWE reuses header parameters and most of the processing
      semantics from JWE.
      Cryptographic algorithms and identifiers used by this specification
      are defined in the JSON Web Algorithms (JWA) <xref target="RFC7518" /> specification.
    </t>
    <t>
      By keeping header parameters in cleartext, the structure is very easy to read.
      However, with cleartext header parameters it is not suitable for all purposes, e.g.,
      transport as HTTP query parameter is not possible without additional
      encoding.
    </t>
    <t>
      Why not build directly on the JWE JSON Format? In the original JWE format
      all data that are to be protected needs to be
      base64url encoded, as a JSON format this becomes a contradiction in itself.
      In the JWE JSON format, base64url encoding only the parts that must be
      protected solves this (most of the data can then be JSON).  By serializing
      the JSON directly for protection it is more direct to serialize the whole
      package including, header parameters, recipients and the encrypted key than just the
      protected header part. Furthermore, this makes reasoning about the
      package easier since the whole thing is protected (not just parts).
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Terminology">
    <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
      when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="EncryptionStructure" title="Encryption Structure">
    <t>
      This section explains how the encryption structure is formed for the
      different cases available.
    </t>
    <t>
      The outermost layer contains equivalants of the JWE header parameters,
      with the addition of <spanx style="verb">recipients</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx>, and <spanx style="verb">ciphertext</spanx> members.
    </t>
    <t>
      Recipients has the same usage as in the JWE JSON encoding, but the structure
      is slightly different. Instead of an object with members <spanx style="verb">header</spanx> and
      <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx>, these have been collapsed. The <spanx style="verb">recipients</spanx> array MUST
      only be included when the message is addressed to multiple recipients.
    </t>
    <t>
      The <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx> member is used in the top-level JSON object when there is only
      one recipient, i.e., the recipients array is not present. When multiple
      recipients are targeted, there is one <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx> value for each of them
      in the recipients array.
    </t>
    <t>
      <figure align="center" anchor="fig:CleartextJWEStructure" title='Cleartext JWE JSON structure'>
        <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{
  <JWE Header Parameters />,
  "recipients": [{
    <JWE Header Parameters />,
    "encrypted_key": "<base64url-encoded data />"
  }],
  "encrypted_key": "<base64url-encoded data />"
  "iv": "<base64url-encoded data />",
  "tag": "<base64url-encoded data />",
  "ciphertext": "<base64url-encoded data />"
}
]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t>
      Depending on the Key Management Mode and number of recipients,
      the structure and members used differs slightly.
    </t>
    <section anchor="SingleRecipient" title="Single recipient">
      <t>
        For the simple case of Direct Encryption mode, parameters <spanx style="verb">alg</spanx>,
        <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">recipients</spanx> are not used
	and <spanx style="verb">kid</spanx> refers to the CEK, if used.
	<xref target="fig:DirectEncryptionExample"/> shows such an example.
        <figure align="center" anchor="fig:DirectEncryptionExample" title='Direct Encryption Example'>
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{
  "enc": "A128CBC-HS256",
  "alg": "dir",
  "kid": "secret-key"
  "iv": "SgD79riBvQPjoRd1sV4Bjg",
  "tag": "kBSE1sRUFqtRXT7iapqEqw",
  "ciphertext": "E8jqajE5MQxwuFCewsxS-2EzA8MU5Ye9kcd52u20RqY"
}
]]>
          </artwork>
	  <!-- TBD The examples should include the keys used so that they can be reproduced and validated -->
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        For the case of Key Encryption mode, a public key has been used to
        encrypt the CEK so <spanx style="verb">alg</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx> members are used here
        but recipients are left out since only of recipient is targeted.
        <xref target="fig:KeyEncryptionExample"/> shows such an
        example.
        <figure align="center" anchor="fig:KeyEncryptionExample" title='Key Encryption Example'>
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{
  "enc": "A128CBC-HS256",
  "alg": "ECDH-ES+A256KW",
  "epk": {
    "kty": "EC",
    "crv": "P-256",
    "x": "EE3a2IBdLB92ePshpcfsN9Yvy7vN63jD33OGZCqY8XY",
    "y": "9bmU509mBNLLSLZAH43TSvfqamjAJIYi4FzdZoG7zdg"
  },
  "encrypted_key": "uqCgVLzgtJU3N7gVHPHv0Jh7gCJI4-3xoKEdlKiK8yKzNS82MzGJJg",
  "iv": "GXZ_hNz0Uct0v8xbB3b_OQ",
  "tag": "f9HDAR_bdRinXAkUJLa6AA",
  "ciphertext": "2as3jE2SWwg4NDg9OrZT_vPMIDHk6MYPKpIl1G959cE"
}
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
	<!-- TBD The examples should include the keys used so that they can be reproduced and validated -->
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="KeyEncryptionExample" title="Two or more recipients">
      <t>
        Two or more recipients can be addressed with key management modes, Key
        Encryption, Key Wrapping and Key Agreement with Key Wrapping. When
        addressing multiple recipients, the <spanx style="verb">recipients</spanx> array is used. The
        <spanx style="verb">recipients</spanx> array contains a list of objects containing needed header parameters
        and an encrypted CEK (<spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx>). Header parameters MUST NOT be present at both
        root and recipients level.

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig:KeyEncryptionExamplewithonerecipient" title='Key Encryption Example with Two Recipients'>
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{
  "enc": "A128CBC-HS256",
  "alg": "ECDH-ES+A256KW",
  "recipients": [{
    "epk": {
      "kty": "EC",
      "crv": "P-256",
      "x": "CIoAhk3bQf2trY0QZWSjyLsmYAUF9p1MDtZz0Fxkp34",
      "y": "FbOuws2RjQQVe3VAlhhYPwbOmpAIl3SM_wq9LVuCt1E"
    },
    "encrypted_key": "UBj97DYItRi_TRdj15jI8G3cv9aefwXO96O3h2BiOwj_wRnCvinC5g"
  },{
    "epk": {
      "kty": "EC",
      "crv": "P-256",
      "x": "B-2YiV42XibVWEohHBYeTOaeW3RSq924oecPfWl-VnA",
      "y": "nWHiI4EnhRQqE-An60tebzUgfwgU9SarWvczE4lSQK8"
    },
    "encrypted_key": "CaWRrVhAsUkGrhy99WjRnXkndB1nD-fmiqs2noOZyC5jYtOohMfUJg"
  }],
  "iv": "lQH2tp9A6BUCNu0YAgYjkQ",
  "tag": "UWv7IpN9rK2xcqrRa8lijw",
  "ciphertext": "UVh2n5qKzfFOttvJ2rCANZUQYp9L7FVbbiYqwRIgpyg"
}
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
	<!-- TBD The examples should include the keys used so that they can be reproduced and validated -->
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="AdditionalAuthenticatedData" title="Additional Authenticated Data (aad)">
      <t>
        As a difference to JWE JSON representation, Cleartext JWE does not have an
        <spanx style="verb">aad</spanx> member. Since Cleartext JWE integrity protects the whole header parameters
        structure it is recommended that one add additional header parameters to protect
        additional cleartext data that needs to be connected to the ciphertext.
        See JWE section 4.2. (Public Header Parameter Names) and 4.3. (Private
        Header Parameter Names) for details on how to add additional header parameters.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="EncryptingandDecryptingCleartextJWEs" title="Encrypting and Decrypting Cleartext JWEs">
    <section anchor="MessageEncryption" title="Message Encryption">
      <t>
        The message encryption process is as follows.  The order of the steps
        is not significant in cases where there are no dependencies between
        the inputs and outputs of the steps.
      </t>
      <t>
        Most steps are equivalent to the ones in JWE.
	Those that have been changed are indicated as such.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Determine the Key Management Mode employed by the algorithm used
            to determine the Content Encryption Key value.  (This is the
            algorithm recorded in the <spanx style="verb">alg</spanx> (algorithm) Header Parameter of
            the resulting JWE.)
          </t>
          <t>
            When Key Wrapping, Key Encryption, or Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping are employed, generate a random CEK value.  See RFC
            4086 [RFC4086] for considerations on generating random values.
            The CEK MUST have a length equal to that required for the
            content encryption algorithm (<spanx style="verb">enc</spanx>).
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Key Agreement or Key Agreement with Key Wrapping are
            employed, use the key agreement algorithm to compute the value
            of the agreed upon key.  When Direct Key Agreement is employed,
            let the CEK be the agreed upon key.  When Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping is employed, the agreed upon key will be used to wrap
            the CEK.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Key Wrapping, Key Encryption, or Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping are employed, encrypt the CEK to the recipient and let
            the result be the JWE Encrypted Key (<spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx>).
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Encryption is employed, let the CEK be the shared
            symmetric key.
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the encoded key value BASE64URL(JWE Encrypted Key).
          </t>
          <t>
            If more than one recipient is being addressed, repeat this process
            (steps 1-7) for each recipient.
          </t>
          <t>
            Generate a random JWE Initialization Vector of the correct size
            for the content encryption algorithm (if required for the
            algorithm); otherwise, let the JWE Initialization Vector be the
            empty octet sequence.
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the encoded Initialization Vector value BASE64URL(JWE
            Initialization Vector).
          </t>
          <t>
            If a <spanx style="verb">zip</spanx> parameter was included, compress the plaintext using
            the specified compression algorithm and let M be the octet
            sequence representing the compressed plaintext; otherwise, let M
            be the octet sequence representing the plaintext.
          </t>
          <t>
            Create the JSON object(s) containing the desired set of Header Parameters,
	    including <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx> if one recipient is addressed
            or the <spanx style="verb">recipients</spanx> array if more than one recipient is addressed.
            (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Serialize the JSON header parameters according to instructions in
            <xref target="Serialization" />. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Let the Additional Authenticated Data encryption parameter be
            the serialized JSON header. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Encrypt M using the CEK, the JWE Initialization Vector, and the
            Additional Authenticated Data value using the specified content
            encryption algorithm to create the JWE Ciphertext value and the
            JWE Authentication Tag (which is the Authentication Tag output
            from the encryption operation).
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the encoded ciphertext value BASE64URL(JWE Ciphertext).
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the encoded Authentication Tag value BASE64URL(JWE
            Authentication Tag).
          </t>
          <t>
            Finalize the encryption by adding the JWE Initialization Vector,
            JWE Authentication Tag and JWE Ciphertext to the JSON
            header parameters and let this be the encrypted package. (modified)
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="MessageDecryption" title="Message Decryption">
      <t>
        The message decryption process is the reverse of the encryption
        process.  The order of the steps is not significant in cases where
        there are no dependencies between the inputs and outputs of the
        steps.  If any of these steps fail, the encrypted content cannot be
        validated.
      </t>
      <t>
        When there are multiple recipients, it is an application decision
        which of the recipients' encrypted content must successfully validate
        for the Cleartext JWE to be accepted.  In some cases, encrypted content for all
        recipients must successfully validate or the Cleartext JWE will be considered
        invalid.  In other cases, only the encrypted content for a single
        recipient needs to be successfully validated.  However, in all cases,
        the encrypted content for at least one recipient MUST successfully
        validate or the Cleartext JWE MUST be considered invalid.
      </t>
      <t>
        Most steps are equivalent to the ones in JWE. Those that has been 
        changed or removed are indicated as such. This is a temporary solution
        to make it easy to spot the difference between JWE and Cleartext JWE,
        It will be removed in final version.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Parse the Cleartext JWE JSON structure. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Extract and remove Cleartext JWE components JWE Initialization Vector (<spanx style="verb">iv</spanx>),
            JWE Ciphertext (<spanx style="verb">ciphertext</spanx>) and JWE Authentication Tag (<spanx style="verb">tag</spanx>).
            Let the remaining JSON be the JWE Protected Header. (added)
          </t>
          <t>
            Base64url decode the encoded representations of the JWE Encrypted
            Key, the JWE Initialization Vector, the JWE Ciphertext, and the
            JWE Authentication Tag, following the restriction that no line
            breaks, whitespace, or other additional characters have been
            used.  (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Verify that the... (removed, JWE step not needed for Cleartext JWE)
          </t>
          <t>
            Let the JOSE Header be the union of the members of the JWE
            Protected Header and the corresponding JWE Per-Recipient Header.
            During this step, verify that the resulting JOSE Header does not
            contain duplicate Header Parameter names.  This restriction includes
            that the same Header Parameter name also MUST NOT occur in distinct
            JSON object values that together comprise the JOSE Header.
            (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Verify that the implementation understands and can process all
            fields that it is required to support, whether required by this
            specification, by the algorithms being used, or by the <spanx style="verb">crit</spanx>
            Header Parameter value, and that the values of those parameters
            are also understood and supported.
          </t>
          <t>
            Determine the Key Management Mode employed by the algorithm
            specified by the <spanx style="verb">alg</spanx> (algorithm) Header Parameter.
          </t>
          <t>
            Verify that the Cleartext JWE uses a key known to the recipient.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Key Agreement or Key Agreement with Key Wrapping are
            employed, use the key agreement algorithm to compute the value
            of the agreed upon key.  When Direct Key Agreement is employed,
            let the CEK be the agreed upon key.  When Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping is employed, the agreed upon key will be used to
            decrypt the JWE Encrypted Key.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Key Wrapping, Key Encryption, or Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping are employed, decrypt the JWE Encrypted Key to produce
            the CEK.  The CEK MUST have a length equal to that required for
            the content encryption algorithm.  Note that when there are
            multiple recipients, each recipient will only be able to decrypt
            JWE Encrypted Key values that were encrypted to a key in that
            recipient's possession.  It is therefore normal to only be able
            to decrypt one of the per-recipient JWE Encrypted Key values to
            obtain the CEK value.  Also, see JWE Section 11.5 for security
            considerations on mitigating timing attacks.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Key Agreement or Direct Encryption are employed, verify
            that the JWE Encrypted Key value is absent.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Encryption is employed, let the CEK be the shared
            symmetric key.
          </t>
          <t>
            Record whether the CEK could be successfully determined for this
            recipient or not.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the more than one recipient is addressed, repeat this process
            (steps 4-12) for each recipient contained in the representation.
          </t>
          <t>
            Serialize the JWE Protected Header according to instructions in
            <xref target="Serialization" />. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Let the Additional Authenticated Data encryption parameter be
            the serialized the JWE Protected Header. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Decrypt the JWE Ciphertext using the CEK, the JWE Initialization
            Vector, the Additional Authenticated Data value, and the JWE
            Authentication Tag (which is the Authentication Tag input to the
            calculation) using the specified content encryption algorithm,
            returning the decrypted plaintext and validating the JWE
            Authentication Tag in the manner specified for the algorithm,
            rejecting the input without emitting any decrypted output if the
            JWE Authentication Tag is incorrect.
          </t>
          <t>
            If a <spanx style="verb">zip</spanx> parameter was included, uncompress the decrypted
            plaintext using the specified compression algorithm.
          </t>
          <t>
            If there was no recipient for which all of the decryption steps
            succeeded, then the Cleartext JWE MUST be considered invalid.  Otherwise,
            output the plaintext.  With multiple recipients, also
            return a result to the application indicating for which of the
            recipients the decryption succeeded and failed. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            If the JSON data structure needs to be verified later, put back the JWE
            Initialization Vector (<spanx style="verb">iv</spanx>), JWE Ciphertext (<spanx style="verb">ciphertext</spanx>) and
            JWE Authentication Tag (<spanx style="verb">tag</spanx>) into the JWE Protected Header.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Finally, note that it is an application decision which algorithms may
        be used in a given context.  Even if a Cleartext JWE can be successfully
        decrypted, unless the algorithms used in the JWE are acceptable to
        the application, it SHOULD consider the Cleartext JWE to be invalid.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Serialization" title="Serialization">
      <t>
        When having header parameters in cleartext serialization of them needs to be
        consistent across platforms. JSON <xref target="RFC8259" /> by itself does not produce
        predictable serialization of data. However, ES6 <xref target="ES6"/> defines how to produce
        JSON that is predictable. By following the ES6 serialization directives,
        one can get predictable results, i.e., the JSON serializer MUST follow the
        directives set out by ES6 when serializing data. The rules defined below
        take the essence from the ES6 specification and list what that means
        in practical terms.
      </t>
      <t>
        Rules for serialization:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            The original property serialization order MUST be preserved as
            described by ECMAScript section 9.1.12.
          </t>
          <t>
            JSON data of the type <spanx style="verb">Number</spanx>, MUST be processed according to
            ECMAScript section 7.1.12.1.
          </t>
          <t>
            Property names MUST NOT be empty ("").
          </t>
          <t>
            Property names MUST be unique.
          </t>
          <t>
            Whitespace must be removed which in practical terms means removal
            of all characters outside of quoted strings having a value of x09,
            x0a, x0d or x20.
	    <!-- What about the ASCII Vertical Tab character (0x0b), which is also whitespace? -->
          </t>
          <t>
            JSON '\/' escape sequences within quoted strings must be treated as
            "degenerate" equivalents to '/' by rewriting them.
          </t>
          <t>
            Unicode escape sequences (\uhhhh) within quoted strings must be
            adjusted as follows: If the Unicode value falls within the
            traditional ASCII control character range (0x00-0x1f and 0x7f), it must
            be rewritten in lowercase hexadecimal notation unless it is one
            of the predefined JSON escapes (\" \\ \b \f \n \r \t) because
            the latter have precedence. If the Unicode value is outside of
            the ASCII control character range, it must be replaced by the
            corresponding Unicode character. ECMAScript section 24.3.2.2.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        When rules have been applied to the example encryption it looks like this
	(with line wraps within values for display purposes only):

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig:NormalizedExample" title='Normalized example'>
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{"enc":"A128CBC-HS256","alg":"ECDH-ES+A256KW","epk":{"kty":"EC",
"crv":"P-256","x":"_DWaWB4PyzglQWEcS9_rHcjzT6u4OcPqQGDw0E4-Wkk",
"y":"5UEVUw9aIICGszcsg_Y1Uem7swqEe3RqgbzSJTpkwow"},
"encrypted_key":"9OQvCTWiL7nVOBq_bp-VHAuaNkIZu6EcsZP9EdawjXBqIqs9"}
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ES6Interoperability" title="ES6+ Interoperability">
      <t>
        For JavaScript optimization reasons, ES6+'s JSON.parse() internally
        rearranges the order of properties with names expressed as integers, making a
        parsed JSON string like '{"2":"a", "A":"b","1":"c"}' actually serialize as
        '{"1":"c","2":"a","A":"b"}'. Due to this fact, signature creators MUST in
        a here unspecified way, "emulate" this scheme since this behavior is not
        intended to be an additional requirement to support by JSON tools in
        general in order to use this specification.
	Note:  This "unspecified" behavior MUST be specified for this spec to become actionable and interoperable!
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <section anchor="IANAJSONHeaderParametersRegistry" title="JSON Header Parameters Registry">
      <t>
        This section registers "ciphertext", "encrypted_key" and "recipients"
        header parameters in the "JSON Web Signature and Encryption Header
        Parameters" registry in the manner described in <xref target="RFC7516"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="IANAJSONHeaderParametersRegistryContents" title="Registry Contents">
        <t>
          <list style='symbols'>
            <t>Header Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">ciphertext</spanx></t>
            <t>Header Parameter Description: The base64url-encoded ciphertext</t>
            <t>Header Parameter Usage Location(s): <spanx style="verb">CT-JWE</spanx></t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Specification Document(s): [this document]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='symbols'>
            <t>Header Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx></t>
            <t>Header Parameter Description: The base64url-encoded encrypted CEK</t>
            <t>Header Parameter Usage Location(s): <spanx style="verb">CT-JWE</spanx></t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Specification Document(s): [this document]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='symbols'>
            <t>Header Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">recipients</spanx></t>
            <t>Header Parameter Description: List of targeted recipients, each with a set of headers</t>
            <t>Header Parameter Usage Location(s): <spanx style="verb">CT-JWE</spanx></t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Specification Document(s): [this document]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
      This specification does (to the author's knowledge), not introduce
      additional vulnerabilities over what is specified for JWE
      <xref target="RFC7516"/>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>
      This document builds on the work done in the JOSE WG so a big thanks goes out
      to all involved in that work. It is specifically inspired by JWE, so a
      special thanks to the authors of that document, Michael B. Jones and
      Joe Hildebrand.
    </t>
  </section>
 </middle>

 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8259'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7516'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7518'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

     <reference anchor="ES6" target="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/6.0/ECMA-262.pdf">
       <front>
         <title>ECMAScript 2015 Language Specification</title>
         <author>
           <organization>Ecma International</organization>
         </author>
         <date/>
       </front>
     </reference>
   </references>

   <section anchor="TestVectors" title="Test Vectors">
     <t>
       TBD
     </t>
   </section>
 </back>
</rfc>
