<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-erdtman-jose-jef-00" ipr="trust200902">
 <front>
   <title abbrev="draft-erdtman-jose-jef">
     JSON Encryption Format (JEF)
   </title>

   <author fullname="Anders Rundgren" initials="A." surname="Rundgren">
     <organization>Independent</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street></street>
         <code></code> <city></city>
         <country>France</country>
       </postal>
       <email>anders.rundgren.net@gmail.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Samuel Erdtman" initials="S." surname="Erdtman">
     <organization>Spotify AB</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Birger Jarlsgatan 61, 4tr</street>
         <code>113 56</code> <city>Stockholm</city>
         <country>Sweden</country>
       </postal>
       <email>erdtman@spotify.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date year="2018" />

   <area>Security</area>

   <workgroup>Javascript Object Signing and Encryption</workgroup>

   <keyword>
     JOSE, Signing, Encryption, Cleartext
   </keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>
       JSON Encryption Format (JEF), represents encrypted content using
       JSON-based data structures. With the use of predictable serialization
       defined in ECMAScript version 6 <xref target="ES6"/> protected headers
       can remain cleartext. JEF reuses headers and most of the processing
       semantics form JWE, but does not directly build on its JSON format.
       Cryptographic algorithms and identifiers for use with this specification
       are described in the separate JSON Web Algorithms <xref target="RFC7518" />.
     </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

<middle>
  <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
    <t>
      JSON Encryption Format (JEF), represents encrypted content using
      JSON-based data structures. With the use of predictable serialization
      defined in ECMAScript version 6 <xref target="ES6"/> protected headers
      can remain cleartext. JEF reuses headers and most of the processing
      semantics form JWE, but does not directly build on its JSON format.
      Cryptographic algorithms and identifiers for use with this specification
      are described in the separate JSON Web Algorithms (JWA).
    </t>
    <t>
      By keeping headers in cleartext the structure is very easy to read.
      However with cleartext headers it is not suitable for all purposes, e.g.
      transport as HTTP query parameter is not possible without additional
      encoding.
    </t>
    <t>
      Why not build directly on the JWE JSON Format? In the original JWE format
      all data that are to be protected needs to be ASCII armored
      (base64url-encoded), as a JOSN format this becomes a contradiction in it
      self. In the JWE JSON format ASCII armoring only the parts that must be
      protected solves this (most of the data can then be JSON).  By serializing
      the JSON directly for protection it is more direct to serialize the whole
      package including, headers, recipients and the encrypted key than just the
      protected header part. Further more this makes reasoning about the
      package easier since the whole thing is protected (not just parts).
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Terminology">
    <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
      when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="EncryptionStructure" title="Encryption Structure">
    <t>
      This section explains how the encryption structure is formed for the
      different cases available.
    </t>
    <t>
      The outermost layer contains the equivalence to JWE headers with the
      addition of "recipients", "encrypted_key", and "ciphertext".
    </t>
    <t>
      Recipients has the same usage as in the JWE JSON format, but the structure
      is slightly different instead of an object with attributes "header" and
      "encrypted_key" these have been collapsed to on. The recipients array MUST
      only be included when the message is addressed to multiple recipients.
    </t>
    <t>
      The "encrypted_key" attribute is used on the root level when there is only
      one recipient i.e. the recipients array is not present. When multiple
      recipients are targeted there is one "encrypted_key" value for each of them
      in the recipients array.
    </t>
    <t>
      <figure align="center" anchor="fig:JEFStructure" title='JEF JSON structure'>
        <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{
  <JWE Headers />,
  "recipients": [{
    <JWE Headers />,
    "encrypted_key": "<base64url-encoded data />"
  }],
  "encrypted_key": "<base64url-encoded data />"
  "iv": "<base64url-encoded data />",
  "tag": "<base64url-encoded data />",
  "ciphertext": "<base64url-encoded data />"
}
]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t>
      Depending on the Key Management Mode and number of recipients the
      structure and used attributes differs slightly.
    </t>
    <section anchor="OneRecipient" title="One recipient">
      <t>
        For the simple case of Direct Encryption mode, parameters "alg",
        "encrypted_key" and "recipients" are not used and "kid" refers to the
        CEK if used. <xref target="fig:DirectEncryptionExample"/> shows such an
        example.
        <figure align="center" anchor="fig:DirectEncryptionExample" title='Direct Encryption Example'>
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{
  "enc": "A128CBC-HS256",
  "kid": "secret-key"
  "iv": "SgD79riBvQPjoRd1sV4Bjg",
  "tag": "kBSE1sRUFqtRXT7iapqEqw",
  "ciphertext": "E8jqajE5MQxwuFCewsxS-2EzA8MU5Ye9kcd52u20RqY"
}
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        For the case of Key Encryption mode a public key has been used to
        encrypt the CEK so "alg" and "encrypted_key" attributes are used here
        but recipients are left out since only of recipient is targeted.
        <xref target="fig:KeyEncryptionExample"/> shows such an
        example.
        <figure align="center" anchor="fig:KeyEncryptionExample" title='Key Encryption Example'>
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{
  "enc": "A128CBC-HS256",
  "alg": "ECDH-ES+A256KW",
  "jwk": {
    "kty": "EC",
    "crv": "P-256",
    "x": "_DWaWB4PyzglQWEcS9_rHcjzT6u4OcPqQGDw0E4-Wkk",
    "y": "5UEVUw9aIICGszcsg_Y1Uem7swqEe3RqgbzSJTpkwow"
  },
  "encrypted_key": "9OQvCTWiL7nVOBq_bp-VHAuaNkIZu6EcsZP9EdawjXBqIqs9",
  "iv": "SgD79riBvQPjoRd1sV4Bjg",
  "tag": "kBSE1sRUFqtRXT7iapqEqw",
  "ciphertext": "E8jqajE5MQxwuFCewsxS-2EzA8MU5Ye9kcd52u20RqY"
}
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="KeyEncryptionExample" title="Two or more recipients">
      <t>
        Two or more recipients can be addressed with key management modes, Key
        Encryption, Key Wrapping and Key Agreement with Key Wrapping. When
        addressing multiple recipients the recipients array are used. The
        recipients array contains a list of objects containing needed headers
        and an encrypted CEK ("encrypted_key"). If a header is present in both
        the root and at recipient level, then recipient level has precedence.

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig:KeyEncryptionExamplewithonerecipient" title='Key Encryption Example with one recipient'>
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{
  "enc": "A128CBC-HS256",
  "alg": "ECDH-ES+A256KW",
  "recipients": [{
    "jwk": {
      "kty": "EC",
      "crv": "P-256",
      "x": "_DWaWB4PyzglQWEcS9_rHcjzT6u4OcPqQGDw0E4-Wkk",
      "y": "5UEVUw9aIICGszcsg_Y1Uem7swqEe3RqgbzSJTpkwow"
    },
    "encrypted_key": "9OQvCTWiL7nVOBq_bp-VHAuaNkIZu6EcsZP9EdawjX"
  },{
    "jwk": {
      "kty": "EC",
      "crv": "P-384",
      "x": "w24AEzLQkT66dkMGaS0ALdRVVV-qWkBY-MnvaE-X8tVfM_rKtCftPnWtj",
      "y": "pRguD1TD-p5CScIg1QgGgOy15BCSjzVmCcOWgR1wuMaCCop559kNz7d"
    },
    "encrypted_key": "D0r_Lnj_397CCPrK_gREltirxstOlt4qQgNC_mHy80c4ODr"
  }],
  "iv": "SgD79riBvQPjoRd1sV4Bjg",
  "tag": "kBSE1sRUFqtRXT7iapqEqw",
  "ciphertext": "E8jqajE5MQxwuFCewsxS-2EzA8MU5Ye9kcd52u20RqY"
}
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="AdditionallyAuthenticatedData" title="Additionally Authenticated Data (aad)">
      <t>
        As a difference to JWE JOSN representation JEF does not have a specific
        "aad" attribute. Since JEF integrity protects the whole header
        structure it is recommended that one add additional headers to protect
        additional cleartext data that needs to be connected to the ciphertext.
        See JWE section 4.2. Public Header Parameter Names and 4.3. Private
        Header Parameter Names for details on how to add additional headers.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="EncryptingandDecryptingJEFs" title="Encrypting and Decrypting JEFs">
    <section anchor="MessageEncryption" title="Message Encryption">
      <t>
        The message encryption process is as follows.  The order of the steps
        is not significant in cases where there are no dependencies between
        the inputs and outputs of the steps.
      </t>
      <t>
        Most steps are equal to the once in JWE, those that has been changed
        are indicated so.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Determine the Key Management Mode employed by the algorithm used
            to determine the Content Encryption Key value.  (This is the
            algorithm recorded in the "alg" (algorithm) Header Parameter of
            the resulting JWE.)
          </t>
          <t>
            When Key Wrapping, Key Encryption, or Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping are employed, generate a random CEK value.  See RFC
            4086 [RFC4086] for considerations on generating random values.
            The CEK MUST have a length equal to that required for the
            content encryption algorithm ("enc").
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Key Agreement or Key Agreement with Key Wrapping are
            employed, use the key agreement algorithm to compute the value
            of the agreed upon key.  When Direct Key Agreement is employed,
            let the CEK be the agreed upon key.  When Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping is employed, the agreed upon key will be used to wrap
            the CEK.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Key Wrapping, Key Encryption, or Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping are employed, encrypt the CEK to the recipient and let
            the result be the JWE Encrypted Key ("encrypted_key").
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Encryption is employed, let the CEK be the shared
            symmetric key.
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the encoded key value BASE64URL(JWE Encrypted Key).
          </t>
          <t>
            If more than one recipient is being addressed, repeat this process
            (steps 1-7) for each recipient.
          </t>
          <t>
            Generate a random JWE Initialization Vector of the correct size
            for the content encryption algorithm (if required for the
            algorithm); otherwise, let the JWE Initialization Vector be the
            empty octet sequence.
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the encoded Initialization Vector value BASE64URL(JWE
            Initialization Vector).
          </t>
          <t>
            If a "zip" parameter was included, compress the plaintext using
            the specified compression algorithm and let M be the octet
            sequence representing the compressed plaintext; otherwise, let M
            be the octet sequence representing the plaintext.
          </t>
          <t>
            Create the JSON object(s) containing the desired set of Header
            Parameters. including "encrypted_key" if one recipient is addressed
            or "recipients" array if more than one recipient is addressed.
            (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Serialize the JOSN headers according to instructions in
            <xref target="Serialization" />. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Let the Additional Authenticated Data encryption parameter be
            the serialized JOSN header. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Encrypt M using the CEK, the JWE Initialization Vector, and the
            Additional Authenticated Data value using the specified content
            encryption algorithm to create the JWE Ciphertext value and the
            JWE Authentication Tag (which is the Authentication Tag output
            from the encryption operation).
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the encoded ciphertext value BASE64URL(JWE Ciphertext).
          </t>
          <t>
            Compute the encoded Authentication Tag value BASE64URL(JWE
            Authentication Tag).
          </t>
          <t>
            Add the "iv", "tag" and "Ciphertext" attributes to the JSON headers
            and let this be the encrypted package. (modified)
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="MessageDecryption" title="Message Decryption">
      <t>
        The message decryption process is the reverse of the encryption
        process.  The order of the steps is not significant in cases where
        there are no dependencies between the inputs and outputs of the
        steps.  If any of these steps fail, the encrypted content cannot be
        validated.
      </t>
      <t>
        When there are multiple recipients, it is an application decision
        which of the recipients' encrypted content must successfully validate
        for the JEF to be accepted.  In some cases, encrypted content for all
        recipients must successfully validate or the JEF will be considered
        invalid.  In other cases, only the encrypted content for a single
        recipient needs to be successfully validated.  However, in all cases,
        the encrypted content for at least one recipient MUST successfully
        validate or the JEF MUST be considered invalid.
      </t>
      <t>
        Most steps are equal to the once in JWE, those that has been changed
        are indicated so.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Parse the JEF JSON structure. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Extract and remove JEF components JWE Initialization Vector ("iv"),
            JWE Ciphertext ("ciphertext") and JWE Authentication Tag ("tag").
            Let the remaining JOSN be the JWE Protected Header. (added)
          </t>
          <t>
            Base64url decode the encoded representations of the JWE Encrypted
            Key, the JWE Initialization Vector, the JWE Ciphertext, and the
            JWE Authentication Tag, following the restriction that no line
            breaks, whitespace, or other additional characters have been
            used.  (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Verify that the... (removed)
          </t>
          <t>
            Let the JOSE Header be the union of the members of the JWE
            Protected Header, and the corresponding JWE Per-Recipient Header.
            During this step, verify that the resulting JOSE Header does not
            contain duplicate Header Parameter names.  This restriction includes
            that the same Header Parameter name also MUST NOT occur in distinct
            JSON object values that together comprise the JOSE Header.
            (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Verify that the implementation understands and can process all
            fields that it is required to support, whether required by this
            specification, by the algorithms being used, or by the "crit"
            Header Parameter value, and that the values of those parameters
            are also understood and supported.
          </t>
          <t>
            Determine the Key Management Mode employed by the algorithm
            specified by the "alg" (algorithm) Header Parameter.
          </t>
          <t>
            Verify that the JEF uses a key known to the recipient.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Key Agreement or Key Agreement with Key Wrapping are
            employed, use the key agreement algorithm to compute the value
            of the agreed upon key.  When Direct Key Agreement is employed,
            let the CEK be the agreed upon key.  When Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping is employed, the agreed upon key will be used to
            decrypt the JWE Encrypted Key.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Key Wrapping, Key Encryption, or Key Agreement with Key
            Wrapping are employed, decrypt the JWE Encrypted Key to produce
            the CEK.  The CEK MUST have a length equal to that required for
            the content encryption algorithm.  Note that when there are
            multiple recipients, each recipient will only be able to decrypt
            JWE Encrypted Key values that were encrypted to a key in that
            recipient's possession.  It is therefore normal to only be able
            to decrypt one of the per-recipient JWE Encrypted Key values to
            obtain the CEK value.  Also, see JWE Section 11.5 for security
            considerations on mitigating timing attacks.
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Key Agreement or... (removed)
          </t>
          <t>
            When Direct Encryption is employed, let the CEK be the shared
            symmetric key.
          </t>
          <t>
            Record whether the CEK could be successfully determined for this
            recipient or not.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the more than one recipient is addressed, repeat this process
            (steps 4-12) for each recipient contained in the representation.
          </t>
          <t>
            Serialize the JWE Protected Header according to instructions in
            <xref target="Serialization" />. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Let the Additional Authenticated Data encryption parameter be
            the serialized the JWE Protected Header. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            Decrypt the JWE Ciphertext using the CEK, the JWE Initialization
            Vector, the Additional Authenticated Data value, and the JWE
            Authentication Tag (which is the Authentication Tag input to the
            calculation) using the specified content encryption algorithm,
            returning the decrypted plaintext and validating the JWE
            Authentication Tag in the manner specified for the algorithm,
            rejecting the input without emitting any decrypted output if the
            JWE Authentication Tag is incorrect.
          </t>
          <t>
            If a "zip" parameter was included, uncompress the decrypted
            plaintext using the specified compression algorithm.
          </t>
          <t>
            If there was no recipient for which all of the decryption steps
            succeeded, then the JEF MUST be considered invalid.  Otherwise,
            output the plaintext.  With multiple recipients, also
            return a result to the application indicating for which of the
            recipients the decryption succeeded and failed. (modified)
          </t>
          <t>
            If packet needs to be verified later, put back the JWE
            Initialization Vector ("iv"), JWE Ciphertext ("ciphertext") and
            JWE Authentication Tag ("tag") into the JWE Protected Header.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Finally, note that it is an application decision which algorithms may
        be used in a given context.  Even if a JEF can be successfully
        decrypted, unless the algorithms used in the JWE are acceptable to
        the application, it SHOULD consider the JEF to be invalid.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Serialization" title="Serialization">
      <t>
        When having headers in cleartext serialization of them needs to be
        consistent across platforms. JSON <xref target="RFC8259" /> by it self does not produce
        predictable serialization of data. However ES6 defines how to produce
        JOSN that is predictable. By following the ES6 serialization directives
        one get predictable results, i.e. the JOSN serializer MUST follow the
        directives set out by ES6 when serializing data. Rules defined below
        takes the essence from the ES6 specification and list what that means
        in practical terms.
      </t>
      <t>
        Rules for serialization of the signed object or object to be signed.
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            The original property serialization order MUST be preserved as
            described by ECMAScript section 9.1.12.
          </t>
          <t>
            JSON data of the type "Number", MUST be processed according to
            ECMAScript section 7.1.12.1.
          </t>
          <t>
            Property names MUST NOT be empty ("").
          </t>
          <t>
            Property names MUST be unique.
          </t>
          <t>
            Whitespace must be removed which in practical terms means removal
            of all characters outside of quoted strings having a value of x09,
            x0a, x0d or x20.
          </t>
          <t>
            JSON '\/' escape sequences within quoted strings must be treated as
            "degenerate" equivalents to '/' by rewriting them.
          </t>
          <t>
            Unicode escape sequences (\uhhhh) within quoted strings must be
            adjusted as follows: If the Unicode value falls within the
            tradditional ASCII control character range (0x00 - 0x1f), it must
            be rewritten in lowercase hexadecimal notation unless it is one
            of the predefined JSON escapes (\" \\ \b \f \n \r \t) because
            the latter have precedence. If the Unicode value is outside of
            the ASCII control character range, it must be replaced by the
            corresponding Unicode character. ECMAScript section 24.3.2.2.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        When rules has been applied to the example encryption it looks like
        this. The output string was folded for improving readability.
        <figure align="center" anchor="fig:NormalizedExample" title='Normalized example'>
          <artwork>
<![CDATA[
{"enc":"A128CBC-HS256","alg":"ECDH-ES+A256KW","jwk":{"kty":"EC",
"crv":"P-256","x":"_DWaWB4PyzglQWEcS9_rHcjzT6u4OcPqQGDw0E4-Wkk",
"y":"5UEVUw9aIICGszcsg_Y1Uem7swqEe3RqgbzSJTpkwow"},
"encrypted_key":"9OQvCTWiL7nVOBq_bp-VHAuaNkIZu6EcsZP9EdawjXBqIqs9"}
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ES6Interoperability" title="ES6+ Interoperability">
      <t>
        For JavaScript optimization reasons, ES6+'s JSON.parse() internally
        rearranges order of properties with names expressed as integers, making a
        parsed JSON string like '{"2":"a", "A":"b","1":"c"}' actually serialize as
        '{"1":"c","2":"a","A":"b"}'. Due to this fact, signature creators MUST in
        an here unspecified way, "emulate" this scheme since this behavior is not
        intended to be an additional requirement to support by JSON tools in
        general in order to use this specification.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>



  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <section anchor="IANAJSONHeaderParametersRegistry" title="JSON Header Parameters Registry">
      <t>
        This section registers "ciphertext", "encrypted_key" and "recipients"
        header parameters in the "JSON Web Signature and Encryption Header
        Parameters" registry in the manner described in <xref target="RFC7516"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="IANAJSONHeaderParametersRegistryContents" title="Registry Contents">
        <t>
          <list style='symbols'>
            <t>Header Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">ciphertext</spanx></t>
            <t>Header Parameter Description: The base64url-encoded ciphertext</t>
            <t>Header Parameter Usage Location(s): <spanx style="verb">JEF</spanx></t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Specification Document(s): [this document]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='symbols'>
            <t>Header Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">encrypted_key</spanx></t>
            <t>Header Parameter Description: The base64url-encoded encrypted CEK</t>
            <t>Header Parameter Usage Location(s): <spanx style="verb">JEF</spanx></t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Specification Document(s): [this document]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='symbols'>
            <t>Header Parameter Name: <spanx style="verb">recipients</spanx></t>
            <t>Header Parameter Description: List of targeted recipients, each with a set of headers</t>
            <t>Header Parameter Usage Location(s): <spanx style="verb">JEF</spanx></t>
            <t>Change Controller: IESG</t>
            <t>Specification Document(s): [this document]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
      This specification does (to the author's knowledge), not introduce
      additional vulnerabilities over what is specified for JWE
      <xref target="RFC7516"/>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>
      This document builds on the work done in JOSE WG so a big thanks goes out
      to all involved in that work. It is specifically inspired by JWE so a
      special thanks to the authors of that document, M. Jones, and
      J. Hildebrand.
    </t>
  </section>
 </middle>

 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8259'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7516'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7518'?>
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

     <reference anchor="ES6" target="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/6.0/ECMA-262.pdf">
       <front>
         <title>ECMAScript 2015 Language Specification</title>
         <author>
           <organization>Ecma International</organization>
         </author>
         <date/>
       </front>
     </reference>
   </references>

   <section anchor="TestVectors" title="Test Vectors">
     <t>
       TBD
     </t>
   </section>
 </back>
</rfc>
